Contact

Caracas, Venezuela +58 0414 3246396 (Mobile) ccolmenaresa@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/zcoder (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Project Management
Project Planning
Outsourcing

Languages

Ingles (Professional Working)
Español (Native or Bilingual)

Certifications

DOS/VSE Control de Sistema English Basic I VM/SP Instalación Moving to VSE/ESA Client/Server Solutions

DOS/VSE Conceptos y Facilidades

Carlos Colmenares A.

IT project engineer, and consulting specialist | IBM Mainframe system programmer & web software developer | ¡Geek! Miranda State, Venezuela

Summary

I have a bachelor's degree in Electronic Engineering, although I have mostly worked as a software engineer or project engineer.

¡Specialist in consulting services!

I have been hired as a specialist consultant for the implementation of complex projects in the areas of IBM Mainframe software engineering and industrial electronic security systems by more than forty (40) national and international corporations, some as prestigious as Registro Nacional de Costa Rica (San Jose, Costa Rica), Banco Invercredito (Bogota, Colombia), PDVSA, Cargill, CANTV, CVG, Metro de Caracas, as well as thirteen (13) banks in Venezuela.

In the past, I worked as a system programmer for IBM Mainframe Technologies at two critical financial institutions. Later, I served as a director of system software at a major North American company with a global presence (Computer Associates, Inc.) dedicated to developing software for IBM Mainframe technologies. Subsequently, throughout my last professional stage, I have had a successful career as a project engineer, designing and installing electronic security systems for public safety and microwave telecommunications.

Another one of my great passions has been web software programming, and in my free time, I develop websites, smartphone applications, and server applications. This hobby constantly requires me to stay updated on new technologies and trends within the web software development ecosystem (Python, Javascript, HTML, CSS, NodeJS, MySQL, MongoDB, APIs, Artificial Intelligence, etc.).

I am available to provide my professional services to a company that needs to develop or consolidate its presence in Latin America or anywhere else in the world, either in person or remotely.

Experience

Self-employed Senior Consultant July 2019 - Present (4 years) Caracas Area, Venezuela

During and after the covid pandemic, I had to reinvent myself.

Goal:

Since then I starting to develop applications for smartphones, PCs, and cloud/desktop servers.

In another way, continue to provide consulting, and maintenance services for those legacy telecommunications and electronic security projects.

Stack:

(by technologies and manufacturers)

*Electronic security systems:

Rosslare, Chiyu, Lenel, Dashou, Dahua, Hikvision.

*Telecommunications:

Ubiquiti, MikroTik, M® Canopy, Cambium Network, VideoComm, Airlive, Trango.

*Web software development:

HTML, CSS, Javascript, React, NodeJS, Python, MySQL, MongoDB, Figma, Git, APIs, etc.

*IBM's Mainframe technologies:

VSE/ESA, VM/ESA, MVS/ESA, OS/390, z/OS. Assembler, VTAM, NCP, CICS, SNA, SDLC, VSAM, JCL, Cobol, JES2, TSO, ACF/POWER, ACF/ICCF, ICKDSF, DB2, DITTO, CA-Vollie, CA-Roscoe, etc.

CYCS Ingeniería e Instalaciones Senior Project Engineer

February 2012 - June 2019 (7 years 5 months)

Caracas, Venezuela

I'm in charge to develop the consulting management area.

Goal:

Design, installation, and training services for network systems, and industrialgrade electronic security systems.

Results:

The success of my management is endorsed, both by the quantity and the technical complexity of the projects successfully executed for large-scale corporate clients.

Projects:

1. Sisven de Venezuela - 1 year

The team leader of installs +1000 cameras of CCTV.

2. Connectix Distribuidora - 2 years

The team leader of installs a lot of surveillance and access control project deployments on its customers.

3. Consultores Cibernéticos - 3 years

The team leader of installs a lot of surveillance and access control project deployments on its customers.

4. ABA tower (Offices Building) - 7 years

Project engineer for all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments.

5. Los Tulipanes Multi-dwelling building - 6 months

Project engineer to install 64 cameras based on the IP Dahua system.

6. MINCI - 1 year

Project engineer to install 256 cameras based on the IP Hikvision system.

7. FITVEN 2013 - 2 months

Project engineer to install a high-level surveillance system (composed of 48 IP cameras) running on a microwave video network for transmission, based on Airlive technologies.

8. DESCA - 1 year

Project engineer to all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments on its customers.

9. CARGILL de Venezuela (USA) - 1 year

Project engineer to install a complex A/C system (based on Chiyu technologies), in each of its sixteen (16) industrial factories across the country.

10. Industrias CEGASA - 3 years

Project engineer to install a complex IP surveillance system running on a microwave video network for transmission, based on Airlive technologies and an A/C system (based on Chiyu technologies); all in its big factory.

11. TORREON tower (Offices Building) - 3 years

Project engineer for all surveillance and A/C systems projects deployments.

CYCS Computing Specialists
Senior Project Engineer
September 1991 - December 2011 (20 years 4 months)
Caracas, Venezuela

I'm in charge to develop the consulting management area.

Goal:

- 1) Capitalize on the highly technical requirements of those clients with IT infrastructure based solely on IBM Mainframe technologies
- 2) Design and installation of Microwave Telecommunications Networks and Industrial-grade Electronic Security Systems.

Results:

The success of my management is endorsed by the extensive hiring of clients for the development of high-level technical projects.

Projects:

1. Instituto Vialidad Estado Vargas - 1 year

Telephony system implementation based on a wireless platform to provide access to PSTN

2. Banco Hipotecario Latinoamericana - 6 months

Design and install a wireless platform to provide Internet access backhaul to its branches

3. Guardia Nacional de Venezuela - 2 years

The TETRA telecommunication platform reengineering

4. Apostadero Naval de Turiamo - 6 months

Design an IP wireless link to connect two military bases and share broadband internet access between them

5. Policía Municipal Estado Vargas - 1 year

Telephony system implementation based on a wireless platform to provide access to PSTN

6. DIEX - 4 years

Design the telecommunication platform to connect all branches with headquarter

7. C-COM de Venezuela (ISP) - 1-year

Motorola's links using canopy radios installation project for its client Microstar

8. Banco Fondo Común - 3 months

Design and installation of a DPL link to connect to another business partner bank

9. Comsat de Venezuela (ISP) - 6 months

VSAT links installation project for its client Miranda EAP

10. Banco Interbank - 4 years

IBM's VM & VSE/ESA operating system technologies project engineering and consulting services

11. Banco Mi Casa EAP - 6 months

IBM's AS/400 infrastructure & software technologies project engineering and consulting services

12. Banco Venezolana EAP - 7 years

IBM's VSE/ESA operating system technologies project engineering and consulting services

SISTEMAS DE COMPUTACIÓN ABACO

System Software Director

May 1984 - August 1991 (7 years 4 months)

Caracas. Venezuela

I was in charge of the system software products area at the North American company Computer Associates, Inc., a world leader in software development for IBM MVS, VM, and VSE operating systems.

Goal:

To provide consulting and product installation services for clients with IBM Mainframe technology.

Results:

The quality of the service provided was endorsed by my hiring by foreign entities, such as Banco Invercredito in Bogota, Colombia, and the National Registry of Costa Rica.

Projects:

Banco La Vivienda EAP - 1 year
 VSE/ESA technical support consulting

2. Latinoamericana de Seguros - 6 months

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

3. Lagoven (a subsidiary of Venezuela's Petroleum) - 3 months

MVS technical support consulting

4. Procter & Gamble de Venezuela - 4 years

VSE/ESA management & technical support consulting

5. Interamericana de Aluminios - 3 years

VM & VSE/ESA Infrastructure & technical support consulting

6. Banco Inverbanco - 1 year

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

7. Banco Caracas - 2 months

MVS/ESA network problems resolution consulting

8. Registro Nacional de Costa Rica (overseas) - 2 weeks

MVS/ESA Problems resolution consulting

9. Ministerio de Infraestructura - 8 months

Windows Server Infrastructure consulting

10. Banco Principal - 6 months

AS/400 capacity planning consulting

11. Banco Fivenez - 4 years

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

12. Banco Hipotecario de Venezuela - 9 years

VSE/ESA technical support consulting

13. Aluminios del Caroní (Alcasa) - 3 years

VSE/ESA technical consulting

14. Banco Exterior - 6 months

VM & MVS telecommunication consulting

15. Empresa 1BC (RCTV) - 9 months

DOS/VSE technical support consulting

16. CANTV - 2 weeks

MVS network problems resolution

17. Banco Invercredito de Colombia (OVERSEA) - 1 week

VM & MVS problems resolution

BANCO MARACAIBO

System Programmer

January 1982 - April 1984 (2 years 4 months)

Estado Zulia, Venezuela

I was in charge of the team of specialists in the technical support division of the computing vice-presidency at the Bank.

Goal:

Among other functions, I was responsible for maintaining the operational status of the computational infrastructure based on IBM Mainframe technology.

..and finally, coordinating with other IT areas for the implementation of new projects, research, testing, and production installation (DevOps) of new versions of operating systems or software packages for both systems and applications.

stack:

- -A s/370 4381, and s/390 9021
- -IBM's VM, VSE, and MVS operating systems running on both mainframes
- -A lot of system software developed by different manufacturers
- -A SNA telecommunication network built to service a lot of bank branches
- -Interconnection links platform with other partner banks

BANCO NACIONAL DE DESCUENTO

System Programmer

January 1977 - March 1981 (4 years 3 months)

Caracas, Venezuela

I was part of the team of specialists in the technical support division of the computing vice-presidency at the Bank.

Goal:

Like my colleagues, we were in charge of keeping the computational infrastructure based on IBM Mainframe technology operational.

Stack:

The IT and computational platform consisted of the following components:

- Two IBM 4381 mainframe technology
- IBM's VM and VSE operating systems running on both mainframe
- A lot of system software developed by several different manufacturers
- A SNA telecommunication network built to service a lot of bank branches
- Interconnection links platforms with other partner banks, and so on.

Education

Universidad Nacional Experimental Politécnica 'Antonio José de Sucre'

Ingeniero Electrónico, Mención Telecomunicaciones · (1976 - 1981)